<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- $Id$ -->

  <sect2 condition="gtk" id="graphical">
  <title>The Graphical Installer</title>
<para>

The graphical version of the installer is only available for a limited
number of architectures, including &arch-title;. The functionality of
the graphical installer is essentially the same as that of the text-based
installer as it basically uses the same programs, but with a different
frontend.

</para><para>

Although the functionality is identical, the graphical installer still has
a few significant advantages. The main advantage is that it supports more
languages, namely those that use a character set that cannot be displayed
with the text-based <quote>newt</quote> frontend. It also has a few usability
advantages such as the option to use a mouse, and in some cases several
questions can be displayed on a single screen.

</para><para arch="any-x86">

The graphical installer is available with all CD/DVD images and with the
hd-media installation method. To boot the graphical installer simply select
the relevant option from the boot menu. Expert and rescue mode for the
graphical installer can be selected from the <quote>Advanced options</quote>
menu. The previously used boot methods <userinput>installgui</userinput>,
<userinput>expertgui</userinput> and <userinput>rescuegui</userinput> can
still be used from the boot prompt which is shown after selecting the
<quote>Help</quote> option in the boot menu.

</para><para arch="any-x86">

There is also a graphical installer image that can be netbooted. And there
is a special <quote>mini</quote> ISO image<footnote id="gtk-miniiso-x86">

<para>
The mini ISO image can be downloaded from a &debian; mirror as described
in <xref linkend="downloading-files"/>.
Look for <filename>netboot/gtk/mini.iso</filename>.
</para>

</footnote>, which is mainly useful for testing.

</para><para arch="powerpc">

For &arch-title;, currently only an experimental <quote>mini</quote> ISO
image is available<footnote id="gtk-miniiso-powerpc">

<para>
The mini ISO image can be downloaded from a &debian; mirror as described
in <xref linkend="downloading-files"/>.
Look for <filename>netboot/gtk/mini.iso</filename>.
</para>

</footnote>. It should work on almost all PowerPC systems that have
an ATI graphical card, but is unlikely to work on other systems.

</para><para>

Just as with the text-based installer it is possible to add boot parameters
when starting the graphical installer.

</para>
<note><para>

The graphical installer requires significantly more memory to run than
the text-based installer: &minimum-memory-gtk;. If insufficient memory is
available, it will automatically fall back to the text-based
<quote>newt</quote> frontend.

</para><para>

If the amount of memory in your system is below &minimum-memory;,
the graphical installer may fail to boot at all while booting the
text-based installer would still work. Using the text-based installer is
recommended for systems with little available memory.

</para></note>
 </sect2>
